<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some legible characters of the faith &amp; love towards the blessed cause &amp; kingdom of Christ worthy to be known and read of all men : some of the last meditations of that faithfull servant of the Lord Mr. Thomas Higgenson, lately deceased a very firm friend (both living and dying) unto the interest and work of the Lord Jesus in these last days.</title>
            <author>Higgenson, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43747</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1949</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11217</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11822484</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11822484</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49600</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43747)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49600)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 496:39)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some legible characters of the faith &amp; love towards the blessed cause &amp; kingdom of Christ worthy to be known and read of all men : some of the last meditations of that faithfull servant of the Lord Mr. Thomas Higgenson, lately deceased a very firm friend (both living and dying) unto the interest and work of the Lord Jesus in these last days.</title>
                  <author>Higgenson, Thomas.</author>
                  <author>Feake, Christopher, fl. 1645-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G.D. for Tho. Brewster ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The epistle to the reader", signed: Chr. Feake.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49600:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49600:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SOME Legible Characters OF FAITH &amp; LOVE Towards the Bleſſed CAUSE &amp; KINGDOM OF CHRIST: Worthy to be known and read of all men.</p>
            <p>Being Some of the laſt Meditations of that Faithfull Servant of the Lord Mr. <hi>Thomas Higgenſon,</hi> lately deceaſed a very firm friend (both living and dying) unto the Intereſt and Work of the Lord Jeſus in theſe laſt days.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſaiah 42.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Behold the former things are come to paſſe, and new things do I declare before they ſpring forth, I tell you of them, ſing unto the Lord a new ſong.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſaiah 43.21.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>This People have I formed for myſelf.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. D.</hi> for <hi>Tho. Brewſter,</hi> and are to be ſould at his Shop at the Sign of the three Bibles in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard. 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:49600:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49600:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Breathings of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt</hi> in the Author of the <hi>enſuing little Treatiſe,</hi> will certainly be very comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and refreſhing to all thoſe, who find any <hi>freſh Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> ſtirring in them to that <hi>Glorious Cauſe</hi> which hath been ſo unworthily and ſo ſhamefully entreated of late years, by an <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatizing Generation.</hi> The <hi>myſticall Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> of their Spirits, which the <hi>King of Saints</hi> is now ſecretly putting in tune, in order to that <hi>harping and ſinging mentioned</hi> Revel. <hi>14.2, 3.</hi> and <hi>15.3.</hi> will be ſo melodious in ſome competent ſpace of time, that
<pb facs="tcp:49600:3"/> many will be very deſirous to learn to ſing and play up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>thoſe inſtruments,</hi> which <hi>David our King, the ſweet ſinger of Iſrael,</hi> hath invented for his Victorious and Tryumphing Followers and Friends. But it was revealed to the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> that <hi>no man could learn that Song, but the hundred four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and four thouſand which were redeemed from the earth.</hi> That, this <hi>Servant of Chriſt</hi> late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deceaſed was much <hi>Redeemed from the earth, and indeed from among men,</hi> and ſo the more capable of ſinging that new ſong before mentioned, is well known to many in this City and elſe where.</p>
            <p>A true eſtimate of the Elevation of this Spirit above the baſe things of the earth, may be eaſily taken by ſuch Artiſts as are well skilled in the Celeſtial or Evangelical Mathematticks; If they do diligently peruſe a <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Treatiſe</hi> of his, called, <hi>Sighs for Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,</hi> penned not long after the <hi>Cromwelian</hi> Apoſtacy and uſurpation. They will find the Spirit that appeareth in thoſe Queries, to be a very ſerious, a very ſavoury, a very penetrating <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>At alſo in thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Treatiſes of his called,</hi> A Lamenting Word. Glory aſar off, now ſtepping in. The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dwellings of the Spirit. A Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony to the True Jeſus.</note> Spirit. And I could wiſh for mine owne part, that the ſubſtance and ſeries of that Diſcourſe were deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:49600:3"/> imprinted in my mind, and in the minds of all thoſe, who do fixedly expect thoſe moſt marvelous Productions, and Mutations which are about to break forth, from the deep Counſels of his will, who is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capitulating or bringing all things to a Head in his Son, <hi>both which are in Heaven, and which are on Earth, even in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I was deſired by ſome of the Authors Friends to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fix a Title and a few words, to the Reader for his own good. But who or what am I? that I ſhould hope to promote any thing of this nature, my very Name being of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive to multitudes, But the day will declare, That the cauſe wherein I have by a moſt bleſsed Conduct imbarked my <hi>Name,</hi> my <hi>Liberty,</hi> my <hi>Eſtate,</hi> my <hi>Life,</hi> my <hi>All,</hi> will make a mends for all thoſe ſcandalous, ſlanderous Reproaches, wherein it was hoped I might have been bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried alive, long before this time of the day. But I know I am (with all I have) in the ſame ſhip with the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and therefore I can <hi>Deſpiſe their Deſpiſings,</hi> who after all their <hi>Inſolent Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage,</hi> have cauſe to be aſhamed of the miſtakes and other pittifull products of their own ſhallow fluid judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, They muſt take their aim better the next time, if they can. As for me, I bleſſe the Lord, that I do ſometimes meet mine own Spirit touched with the <hi>Magnetick vertue</hi> of the Spirit of Chriſt in the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes
<pb facs="tcp:49600:4"/> and Writings of others, whoſe Spirits were found faithful <hi>in the day of Rebuke and Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> which hath paſſed over us, in the number of whom I reckon this <hi>dear diſceaſed Friend</hi> to be one. And could have wiſhed, that the <hi>Following Papers</hi> might have been perfected and publiſhed by himſelf, before his departure: In regard that ſeverall <hi>advantages,</hi> and <hi>elegancies</hi> will be found, by judicions Readers, to be very much wanting, through many miſpointings, mistakes, and errataes, which were paſt cure before they came to my hand. Nevertheleſſe, I ſhall do the beſt office I can <hi>to ſerve in love,</hi> both his living Readers, and my deceaſed Friend, by rectifying ſome things which are amiſſe, as in the <hi>Errataes</hi> following.</p>
            <p>All is commended to the Bleſsing of him, <hi>who worketh all things after the Counſell of his own will,</hi> no more at the preſent, Reader, from</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Friend and Servant for the Lords ſake, CHR. FEAKE.</signed>
               <dateline>London <date>this <hi>6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                     </hi> of the <hi>4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                     </hi> moneth, <hi>1659.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge 10. line 36. read <hi>one of the lorns.</hi> pag. 11. l. ult. r. <hi>againſt Babilon.</hi> p. 12. l. 19. r. <hi>whereof</hi> p. 9. l 1. dele <hi>as.</hi> p. 20. l. 14. for <hi>as</hi> r. <hi>and.</hi> l. ult. for <hi>off</hi> r. <hi>of.</hi> p. 21. l. 11 dele <hi>how.</hi> p. 22. l. 12. r. <hi>with clay.</hi> l. 21. make a (,) at law. l. 33. r. <hi>unſuitable.</hi> p. 23. 2. r. <hi>near.</hi> l. 32. r. <hi>when</hi> p. 25. l. 32. r. <hi>alone.</hi> p. 32. l. 25. r. <hi>loſſe.</hi> l. ult. dele <hi>of.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49600:4"/>
            <head>SOME LEGIBLE CHARACTERS OF FAITH and LOVE towards The Bleſſed CAUSE &amp; KINGDOM OF CHRIST, Worthy to be known and read of all men.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S God has in every Age had ſome ſpecial work upon the wheel, and as the ſame has ever been attended with much oppoſition, difficulty and offence, ſo he has alwayes given to ſome of his Servants an eye to ſee and be affected with it, and to put their helping hand unto it: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the things, which have been of late the Travel of many, and yet are of ſome amongſt us, being of ſuch weight and worth, of ſuch bleſſed and glorious conſequence, would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire men of a more excellent ſpirit, and skilful hand, to ſet them forth in their proper beauty and luſtre; yet ſuch ſervice as I had, love conſtrained me to offer, eſpecially at this time, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Exigencies of Truth call for ſomewhat at our hands. If unbelief, ſecurity and revolt had not choaked that Faith, Light, and Love, unto the Lord and his preſent Works in the World, whereby many among us were led out to undertake and effect great things in purſuance thereof, that Truth would by this time have been witneſs of it ſelf in reall effects to the face of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49600:5"/> the world, and would not have needed a vindication of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by word or argument, to wit, <hi>That God is doing new and extraordinary things in this day in the earth:</hi> To obtain clearneſs and certainty in which point is of high concernment, unto all ſuch as would not be left in the dark, concerning the great deſignations of Providence, and their own duty, and as would be led out through that confuſion at this day among us, of contrary principles, affections, and intereſts, unto a right Judgement therein; it being to be rationally concluded, that if all things are to continue as they were, and no new thing to be done, that then thoſe high Intereſts lately contended for, and all wayes and means put in practiſe for the obtaining thereof, are to be condemned, as which had a tendencie to introduce a new ſtate of things, and the preſent courſe into which things are ſince put is rather to be juſtified, as tending to reduce us unto the old; as on the other hand, if the Lord has not yet brought forth that which he intended in his mighty Works a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, and has further things to do, this may be a founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of encouragement unto all the Friends and Followers of Chriſt, to proceed in their former Faith, Fervency, Prayer, and in all ſuitable wayes and means for the help and furtherance thereof, notwithſtanding the unbelief, oppoſition, and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of preſent viſible proceedings contrary thereunto.</p>
            <p>The grounds we have to hold out for our belief and hope in this thing, that God hath been, and is in theſe dayes, doing ſome new and extraordinary things, are,</p>
            <p>Firſt, A freſhneſs of ſpirit that hath been among us: <hi>Zech.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Not by might, nor by power, but by my Spirit, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts:</hi> The experience of former and latter Ages may tell us, that God has had his times of going away and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to his Place, leaving his People and the World without any viſible tokens or eminent appearances of his Power, in ſuch ſeaſons the Spirit has run low and faint, only in ſuch a meaſure as might preſerve his People in a life of conflict and warfare; and his times of coming forth again out of his Place, when he has had ſome new work to do, and then has he alwayes given a new and freſh Spirit, ſuitable to the work he had in hand: It is ſaid, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.13, 14. <hi>The Spirit of the Lord came upon David from that day forward, but the Spirit of the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49600:5"/> from Saul, and an evil ſpirit from the Lord troubled him.</hi> The like was ſeen in our dayes: While the Lord took away his Spirit from many Wiſe, Mighty, and Noble among us, and ſent darkneſs, famine, and withering into their hearts, and confuſion upon their counſels; at the ſame time he put a Spirit of Faith and Power upon a deſpiſed ſort of men, which was as marrow and fatneſs to their bones. There is a word in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 10.27. <hi>The yoak ſhall be deſtroyed becauſe of the anointing.</hi> The principal end and effect of the divers and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Diſpenſations of Spirit, which God has renewed to former Generations, at leaſt in later times, has been to regain unto Chriſt and his Church, out of the hands of Antichriſt, ſome of thoſe rights and concernments, which during the long time of darkneſs and tyranny, have been concealed, or forcibly detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from them: The like effect had that Spirit that was put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a People among us: Many pretious Truths and Priviledges, the light and comfort whereof was denyed to our fore-fathers, were diſcovered, and many heavy yokes of ſpiritual and civil bondage, long continued upon their necks, were broken and deſtroyed by that Spirit that remained among us: Oh what bleſſedneſs did this Spirit bring with it, if it be but remembred, what light and certainty it gave of the preſence of God with us? what diſcerning of the time? what a ſtrong ſavour and relliſh of ſpiritual things? and what earneſt longings and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings after a better ſtate of things built upon the foundations of Righteouſneſs and Truth? The clear ſhining forth of new Covenant light out of the former miſts of Antichriſtian obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, was that which begot this Spirit in the hearts of many; the ſetting up of Chriſt in the more full and unlimited exerciſe of his Kingly Power and Authority over all things, both in Church and Nation, was that end it preſſed after; the taking out of the way all Parties and Intereſts that had or might hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the obtaining of this end, was that work it was with much zeal and ſucceſs exerciſed about: Such a freſhneſs of ſpirit was never, nor can it be conceived was of late given forth, but in order to the uſhering in ſome new and further work into the World.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The works of Providence drawn out in a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued line and ſeries of deliverances unto a praying People, next
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49600:6"/> unto thoſe inward impreſſions of the quickening Spirit, are a ſignal teſtimony unto us, that God is doing ſome new and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thing in the World: When the Works of God in a Nation grow up to that height and eminency, as like a tide to bear down all before them; then they are to be obſerved and heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as ſignes and tokens, as the Voice of God unto that people, ſignifying what are his preſent Counſels and Works he is deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to do: It is ſaid in the <hi>Pſalm</hi> 105.26, 27, 28. <hi>He ſent Moſes his ſervant, and Aaron whom he had choſen, they ſhewed his ſignes among them, and wonders, in the Land of Ham: He ſent darkneſs and made it dark, and they rebelled not againſt his Word:</hi> The Signs God wrought for <hi>Iſrael</hi> upon <hi>Egypt,</hi> and his Appearances for them in the Wilderneſs, did ſhew, that the time of their Redemption was come, that he would bring them to the promiſed Reſt: Once it was that the Lord kept us under a low condition of ſpirit, faith and courage, and as to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Man under a ſtate of ſubjection and ſuffering, under the heavy yoaks of the Antichriſtian Task-maſters, and for a long time held his peace, leaving us without any ſignes and tokens in a viſible way; then was a time for us to ſit ſtill, things being dark while the Lord was ſilent; but having been ſince raiſed up into hopes and expectations, that a day and time of great things was at hand, and this not the work of fancies, but of the Spirit, of Faith and Prayer, upon the foundation of glorious Promiſes; and God alſo having gone before us in many emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent appearances one upon another, all tending to make way for the bringing in ſome better thing then yet is ſeen: This is unto us, one among other, the ſober and good grounds we have, to proceed in prayer and waitings for that Excellent State of things to break forth, whereof ſome former taſtes and glimpſes we have had already, the preſent interruption and ſtop put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the work to the contrary notwithſtanding. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith, <hi>Chap.</hi> 43.3. <hi>I gave Egypt for thee, Ethiopia and Sheba for thee:</hi> May it not be ſaid, that the Lord gave whole Nations in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our hands, and all thoſe parties that roſe up one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, upon this account, becauſe they ſet themſelves againſt a Cauſe and People that God had among us? Let us but obſerve who all thoſe that have appeared in evill will and deſigns a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Cauſe, have been ſadly left of God, unto darkneſs,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49600:6"/> and waſting in their ſpirits, counſels and proceedings, the very report whereof put a fear upon the Nations about, while lie owned, and bleſſed, and comforted his People, by a glorious leading Preſence among them: What is the meaning of theſe things? Is there not a far other more Excellent State of things ſignified, and intended hereby, then the preſent frame of things of late ſet up, under which worldly pomp and policy, the old oppreſſive and corrupt Intereſts of former worldly States and Governments, with a too general defection of many from their firſt light, love, and purity, is ſpringing and growing up again in the Land.</p>
            <p>The changes that of late have paſſed over us, are a further Teſtimony from God unto us, that he is doing ſome new thing in the Earth: It is ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.10. <hi>The Scepter ſhall not depart from Judah, nor a Law-giver from between his feet, until Shiloh come.</hi> The firſt coming of our Saviour was uſhered in by a change upon all Nations, the <hi>Romans</hi> poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelves of the Kingdome of <hi>David,</hi> and of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the whole World: <hi>Joel</hi> ſaith, <hi>chap.</hi> 2.30, 31. <hi>I will ſhew wonders in the Heavens, and in the Earth, bloud, and fire, and pillars of ſmoak; the Sun ſhall be turned into darkneſs, and the Moon into bloud, before the great and the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible day of the Lord come:</hi> We are to know the ſecond coming of the Lord Jeſus to ſet up his Kingdom on Earth draws near, when we ſee changes coming upon the whole frame of things, both in Church and State: This Nation, a Nation wherein Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion is reformed unto the greateſt degree of Light and Purity of any Nation in the World; yet how has it been turned up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide down? How have the Heavens of our more reformed, as well as the Earth of our more looſe corrupted Church-ſtate been ſhaken? How has the Sun of Monarchy, Kings and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, been darkened, and the Moon of our Civil State been turned into bloud? How have formes of Government, and Authorities, haſtily riſen up one after another, and have as faſt diſſolved in weakneſs and confuſion: <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.1. <hi>I ſaw a new Heaven and a new Earth, for the firſt Heaven and the firſt Earth were paſſed away, and there was no more Sea:</hi> When the Governments, Kingdoms, and Common-wealths, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out both the Antichriſtian and the more Reformed Nations, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49600:7"/> unſettled, ſhaken, and falling in pieces, it is a ſign they are grown old in ſin and guilt, and as fit for no more uſe are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be done away: The time for the fulfilling of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie ſeems at the very door, <hi>Revel.</hi> 14.15. <hi>Thruſt in thy ſickle and reap, for the time is come for thee to reap, for the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt of the earth is ripe.</hi> Who ever ſaw the Nations round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout us in ſuch a poſture of warr and wrath as at this day, ſo fitted for deſtruction? What Earthquakes, Eclipſes, Comets, raining of Bloud, and raging Peſtilences, have there been of late? How is the whole Creation ſenſible of the drawing near of the Lord Jeſus, whoſe coming in the Spirit of Grace and Glory in his People, and in Wrath and Judgements againſt his Enemies, is that which cauſeth all theſe changes which have been, and are yet to be in the World.</p>
            <p>It is well known to many, that both the ſpiritual and viſible Intereſt of Chriſt hath begun to ſhine forth more of late in this Nation, and God hath given more viſible teſtimonies in a way of owning of it here then in any other Nations beſides: So ſoon as this Intereſt and Cauſe was placed among us, what a ſeries of changes did preſently flow in upon us? What com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions were ſtirred up againſt us from abroad? and how are all the Nations about us ſince put into a flame? Nations long ſettled upon their lees of Antichriſtian blindneſs and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when God begins to empty ſuch from veſſel to veſſel, to bring upon them one breach and change after another, it is a ſign he has ſome new and ſpecial thing to do with ſuch People: Oh that we might ſee the Lord Jeſus, as he comes forth through theſe things, and lifts up himſelf ſtill more and more by them.</p>
            <p>The Refinings that have attended our changes have a freſh ſignificancy with us, that God is about ſome new and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary things among us; every change was as a fire purifying the ſucceeding parties into a more refined Spirit and Principles, then thoſe that were before; as new work and new difficulties were preſented, while many went off, their hearts failing them, through darkneſs, wearineſs, or fear, a new Spirit was put upon others in a freſh ſupply of light and ſtrength, giving a more piercing ſight into the excellency of the intereſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49600:7"/> and cauſe in hand, and further Reſolution to preſſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards towards it.</p>
            <p>Principles in the beginning of the day were dim and weak, both in the Civil and Military Inſtruments, carrying them forth a little higher then unto the Intereſt of meer civil right and freedome, againſt the Arbitrarines and exceſs of Monarchy and Prelatical Church ſtate; theſe Generations being moſt of them laid aſide, a choicer People were raiſed up in their place, of clearer Principles and higher Aymes, calling for Impartial Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, removal of burdens, dethroning of Kingly Power, aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Worldly Pomps and Splendour, a Religious Magiſtracy, a Spiritual Miniſtry, liberty of Worſhip, &amp;c. they had ſo much light, as to diſcern the preſent frame of things to be exceedingly corrupted with Antichriſtian mixture, and to ſee there was a better ſtate of things to be had framed and acted, not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Humane Reaſon, and <hi>Prudentials of State,</hi> in the hands of men, as men, but according to the Decrees and Laws of Chriſt, in the hands of men, as ſpiritual and Saints.</p>
            <p>Further, changes ſo far heightened this Principle, as that the Intereſt and Right of Jeſus Chriſt, to exerciſe a Kingly Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity over the Kingdomes of men, was publickly and ſolemnly owned for a reaſon among us; let it be obſerved, how the Lord winnowed and purged one party after another; how the ſaid old, dark, and corrupt faſhion of things was a going away, and a new face of things began to appear with a new luſtre, both upon Church and State, upon Doctrine and Worſhip; garments of mourning and bondage formerly upon the People of God, changed into a ſtate of liberty and gladneſs; a looſe and worldly Church reformed firſt to the letter, after to a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of ſpirituality; the conteſt begun for a civil Intereſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined into a conteſt for ſpiritual Faith, Prayer, and expectations in many riſing higher and higher, firſt for civil liberty, then for a ſpiritual, after for the Kingdom and Government of Jeſus Chriſt: And here that word may not unſeaſonably be minded, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.13, 14. <hi>Though ye have lain among the pots, yet ſhall ye be as the wings of a Dove covered with ſilver, and her feathers with yellow gold; when the Almighty ſcattered Kings in it, it was white as ſnow in Salmon;</hi> When the time came, that the Lord would ſcatter and bring down all thoſe Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49600:8"/> Powers, and Parties, that had held his Church in this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at the Brick-kills, in the condition of Servants and Bond-men, then did he take off our filthy garments, and clothed us with change of Rayment, high Reformation, Victories, and many viſible Teſtimonies of his Preſence among us, and all theſe as Earneſts or firſt-fruits of that flouriſhing State, which ſhall be brought forth in the Coming and Kingdom of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Iſraels</hi> Redemption out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> mention was firſt made of a civil Intereſt only, of their deliverance from the burdens and oppreſſions of that King, but the principal thing intended was, that God himſelf would be their King: If this was a typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal <hi>Preludium</hi> of the State of the Church in theſe laſt dayes, as that Propheſie ſeems to imply; <hi>I will reſtore thy Judges as at firſt, and thy Counſellors as at the beginning:</hi> If ſo, then a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from the yoaks of Tyranny and Perſecution, unto a condition of meer outward liberty and quiet, was not the chief Reſult in ended us in our changes, but that God would thereby bring us both Church and State under a more immediate Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to his Son, that he alone ſhould be our Law-giver, King, and Judge, ruling us according to his own Word and Spirit, not according to the Prudentials and Policies of this World: If the Lord has thus kindled a Refining fire among us, let us take heed how we quench it, till our purification, thereby preparing us unto that Kingdom and Glory that is drawing near.</p>
            <p>The Lord hath taken new and extraordinary wayes with us; beſides that peculiar eye that hath watched over the Engliſh Nation, in former times, to ſave it from the bloud-thirſty Rage of Antichriſtian Adverſaries, their Invaſions from abroad, and Conſpiracies at home: God has of late made this Nation, as it were, a Stage, whereupon he came forth, and began that Cup of the Wine of his Wrath againſt the Kingdomes and Monarchies of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that is determined againſt them; here began the Horns of Antichriſt to be thrown down; here the ſpiritual and civil Liberties and Rights of Saints and Men were more viſibly owned of God, againſt the Injuſtice and Uſurpations of Eccleſiaſtical and Temporal Rulers, then had been before; here the Office of Chriſt, as Prophet and Head of his Church,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49600:8"/> was vindicated and advanced above the Commandements and Laws of Men to the contrary. The Authority of Chriſt, as King of Saints and Nations, and the right of Saints with him to Rule and Judge the World, has gained more Reputation and acceptance with us then all the World over: God ſpeaks con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Church in the latter dayes, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 43.18. <hi>Remember ye not the former things, neither conſider the things of old, behold I will do a new thing:</hi> And what was that new thing? <hi>For your ſakes I have ſent to Babylon, and have brought down all their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> ver. 19. <hi>I will even make a way in the wilderneſs, and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers in the deſert,</hi> Chap. 44.3. <hi>For I will pour water upon him that is thirſty, and flouds upon the dry ground; I will pour my Spirit upon thy ſeed, and my bleſſing upon thine off-ſpring:</hi> The Lord had a People among us, who he formed for his praiſe; how did he for their ſake bring down our Princes and Nobles, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramours and Lovers of <hi>Babylon?</hi> How was our Land, which had layen like a wilderneſs for want of Goſpel light and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of Juſtice, turned into Rivers of water, through Righteouſneſs, Knowledge, and the Preſence of the Lord, ſhining forth among us? And in that day what a ſprinkling of the Spirit was there upon the dry ground, upon many Sons and Daughters among us, of ſimple and low capacities, weak and fooliſh things, whereby many wiſe, mighty, and honorable, were put to confuſion, and brought to nothing? Let us call to mind what a Preſence was with us in the fields; what impulſions of the Spirit, as of a mighty wind, were upon many, carrying them up, beyond themſelves, through difficulties and dangers? What a Spirit of Judgment was put upon many, to bind Kings in chains, and Nobles in fetters of iron? What a light of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of the Glory of Chriſt ſhined round about us? What melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and yernings were ſeen throughout all, even the darkeſt corners of the Land, under the ſenſe of a crucified Saviour? What Lightenings among the People of God, and what Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes upon their Enemies? Such things as made us a terror and wonderment to all the Nations about us; ſpeak oh ye Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins that are fallen aſleep, if theſe be ordinary Diſpenſations, if ye have read or heard of a parallel? if not, then look upon them, as beginnings of greater things yet to come to paſſe.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:49600:9"/>
            <p>But if any ſhall ſay; <hi>Why may not this glory ſet in a cloud, as great things were done, and as great hopes and expectations rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in</hi> Germany, <hi>yet all came to nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer; <hi>Luther</hi> lived to ſee his Doctrine prevailed over many Cities and Countries, and ſoon after his death brake out the Warr in that Nation, for the puniſhment of them that were Adverſaries to the Goſpel; when that Light was quenched there, it ſprung forth with renewed ſtrength in this our Iſland, and has ever kindled ſuch a fire, as has at ſundry times couſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the chiefeſt part of the Riches, ſtrong Holds, and Yoaks of Antichriſt that were among us.</p>
            <p>God has begun the influences and effects of ſome of the laſt and glorious Promiſes in our Nation; Providences and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies have been as teeming wombs, bringing forth the firſt fruits of great things amongſt us; The Promiſes that concern the Church of Chriſt, towards the end of her wilderneſs ſtate, do ſpeak of great changes and revolutions to come to paſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that time in the Antichriſtian States and Kingdoms, with their Governments and Affairs, that by theſe tempeſts this old corrupt frame of things may be broken, and fall, and way made for a glorious State of things, to be brought forth in the fuller exaltation of Jeſus Chriſt; <hi>A Stone ſhall be cut out without hands, that ſhall ſmite the great Image upon his feet: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the ſervants and upon the hand-maids in thoſe dayes will I pour out my Spirit, and theſe ſhall hate the Whore, and ſhall make her deſolate and naked, and ſhall eat her fleſh, and burn her with fire; then the earth ſhall rele to and fro like a drunkard, and ſhall be removed like a cottage, and the Lord ſhall puniſh the Hoaſt of the high ones that are on high, and the Kings of the earth upon the earth: Then the Moon ſhall be confounded, and the Sun aſhamed.</hi> If theſe Promiſes have begun their effects upon us in this Nation, then let us know, that the way of the Lord amongſt us is new, and his work extraordinary; let us remember what a ſprinkling of a gracious, choice and active Spirit has been among us: what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent things were done while it was freſh upon us? How Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy and Prelacy was cut off, as out of the horns of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt? How the Stone has been at work among us, whereby that whole Church and State, with the pomp, power, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it was overturned? What Parties and Inſtruments were
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49600:9"/> laid aſide, as being ſhort of ſpirit for the buſineſs of that day? and what Laws, Conſtitutions, and Cuſtoms were caſt off, as Antichriſtian, and oppoſite to the work then in hand: Add to all theſe, what a mighty Witneſs of God unto all theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in a continued ſeries of Salvations and Victories over all that roſe up againſt us; and then may we not conclude, That the things that were then on foot among us, were the firſt fruits and earneſts of thoſe precious Promiſes, and not (as too much cauſe has of late been given to ſay) the productions of poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, headineſs or deluſion; to ſay nothing, what moſt deep and ſweet impreſſions were upon our hearts from the word of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, concerning the Kingdom of Chriſt, and downfal of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> we have had two obſervable ſigns, that the time, or the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, wherein the Lord will do great things, is at hand; the one is a moſt peculiar and diſtinguiſhing preſence of the Lord, by inward Refreſhings of Spirit, and outward Diſpenſations of Mercy, which was with us whilſt our hearts went after the Lord; and our Principles and Proceedings were in a ſubſerviency to his Cauſe and Kingdom; when others, whoſe aims and ends were more National and mixt with worldly intereſt, were laid aſide, left in the dark, and under viſible rebukes. So great a difference has the Lord made between theſe, who ſat down in a meer civil and worldly Reformation, and others, who preſſed after better hopes, <hi>(viz)</hi> the fulfilling of Promiſes, and a full ſubjection of all things to the Word and Spirit, muſt needs be taken for a ſingular Evidence to give light unto us, which way the work and deſign of the Lord lies at this day. The other ſign is, the ſad clouds of diſpleaſure that are now upon us; that gracious and lively preſence that brought us out from our former Egyptian darkneſs and ſlavery, and by a ſtrong hand led us through many dark and difficult paths in the beginning of the day, is much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from off our Councils, Camp, &amp; ſolemn Aſſemblies; Laws are given unto us that are not good, and Statutes whereby we cannot live; our Rulers are many of them ſuch as know not <hi>Joſeph,</hi> the faithful Servants of Chriſt, ſuch as had no heart unto or communion with that great Affair and Intereſt of Chriſt once on foot; the Military Power, which was as a new ſharp threſhing Inſtrument againſt us: <hi>Babylon</hi> is now become a prey to the Heathen, or as Hirelings under a forreign Prince;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49600:10"/> the cauſe and truth once ſo dear and highly owned, now as to any viſible progreſs of it, under a ſentence of death, ſo that we may ſay, we have ſown much, and bring in little; we looked for much, and lo it comes to little; the Lord hath blown upon it, becauſe his Houſe lies waſt. <hi>Haggai</hi> proved to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> That the viſible diſcountenance that was upon all their publick and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate concernments, from the Lord, was a ſign, That the time was come, that the Lords Houſe ſhould be built; even ſo clouds of diſpleaſure from God returning again, after ſuch a morning of ſucceſſes and bleſſings as has been upon us, ought to be a ſign unto us, that the Lord hath great things yet to do among us; and that it is time for us to awake, and go on with the Work that has been begun among us.</p>
            <p>Now let us enquire what Works the Lord is about, and wherein his Saints ſhould be found waiting upon him at this day; there are ſome Rules, which in this Point have given light unto the Church of God in former Ages, and lately in our time, and may be further uſeful to us in this day for our ſatisfaction herein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt Rule.</hi> The Word, upon which we were made to hope in the day of our greateſt difficulties and ſtraits, and in the ſtrength and comfort wherein we ſuffered ſo many things; when God ſets it upon the heart of his People to wait for ſome word, ſome ſpiritual Promiſe to be made good, and to undergo many things for the obtaining thereof, that is the Work of that day; God made a Promiſe to <hi>Abraham</hi> four hundred and fifty years afore it came to paſſe, when the time of the Promiſe drew nigh, God put it upon <hi>Moſes</hi> heart; after him upon <hi>Joſhuah,</hi> to go up and poſſeſs the good Land. <hi>David</hi> had a Word that he ſhould be King, he bore up himſelf upon this word through a long ſeries of conflicts and troubles, till the things was done. In the late Warrs, thoſe who bare the burden and heat of that day, had a Word, whereupon they leaned, which conſiſted of many Promiſes, ſhewing a more full and glorious Reformation to be ſet up in the World, wherein Jeſus Chriſt in all his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Laws, and Commands, ſhould be more viſibly own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and exalted, and <hi>Babylon</hi> in all her intereſts thrown down: This was that Word that was a Guide and a Strength to many among us in the troubles and perplexities of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49600:10"/> that day, and not the Policy and Power of this World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Second Rule.</hi> Obſerve of what nature were theſe breathings of the Spirit, and the impreſſions that were wrought thereby upon the moſt enlightened, faithful and praying part of the People, while we were following God in the way of his Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments among us; the Work God is about begins in the heart of his People, for if the Secret of the Lord is with them that fear him; when a People are in the Work of God, following Jeſus Chriſt through many ſore Tryals and hardſhips, then ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve what things in that day lay with moſt weight upon their hearts, and what the ſtirrings and movings of the Spirit with the Word were then amongſt them, and there the Work of God her: <hi>Pſalm</hi> 102.13, 14. <hi>Thou ſhalt ariſe and have mercy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Sion, for the time to favour her, yea the ſet time is come, for thy Servants take pleaſure in her ſtones, and favour the duſt thereof:</hi> When God begins to awake the ſpirit of his People, to call them out of their darkneſs, ſecurity, and carnal intereſts, and puts upon them a gracious ſenſe of the condition of <hi>Sion,</hi> and to look, and long, and cry to the Lord for her building up, then is the time at hand; 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11. When the Lord would turn the Kingdom from the Houſe of <hi>Saul</hi> unto <hi>David,</hi> then he ſtirred up all <hi>Iſrael</hi> to come and make <hi>David</hi> King: It may be obſerved, whilſt the Spirit of the Lord remained in the lively and freſh gales and actings of it upon our publick Inſtruments, and Camp, Council, and Aſſemblies, there was ſuch a ſenſe upon their hearts, that the Kingdom of Chriſt might be promoted both in Civils and Spirituals, and the remaining poſts and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, all the limbs and branches of Antichriſtianiſme, might be broke to pieces, and carried them with a lively zeal and courage through all oppoſitions, difficulties, and temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations in that day to the contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Third Rule.</hi> Conſider which way the Works of Providence looked, that were formerly done amongſt us, and whither they tended, though Providence, when it is alone, is not any certain Rule to go by; yet when the Works of God and his Word and Spirit go altogether, when a People have his Word and Spirit ſtirring them up unto a Work, and Providences coming in one upon another to carry them out in it, then are Providences to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49600:11"/> be heeded, as ſigns of the times, and of the Work God is about; <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 105.26. <hi>He ſent Moſes his Servant, and Aaron whom he had choſen, they ſhewed his ſigns among them, and wonders in the Land of Ham.</hi> The Works God wrought for <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Egypt</hi> and the Wilderneſſe, was as Gods manifeſtation to the Nations, who were his People, and what he was about; when a People are engaged in a cauſe upon holy and righteous Principles, the Promiſes, Prophecies and Truths of the latter dayes, and God is ſeen going forth before them, working glorious Deliverances for them, this is a lowd Teſtimony: What is the Work God is determined to do in ſuch a day? <hi>Pſalm</hi> 105.14, 15. <hi>He ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered no man to do them wrong, yea he reproved Kings for their ſakes, ſaying, touch not mine Annointed, and do my Prophets no harm:</hi> How like to this the dealing of God with <hi>England</hi> of late have been may appear, whoſoever ſhall remember what an eye of peculiar reſpect and favour the Lord had upon a People among us, what a choice and bleſſed Spirit a deſpiſed People had, whereby many wiſe and honourable among us were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded? What power to bind Kings in chains, and Nobles in fetters of iron? How no weapon that was formed againſt them could proſper: Moreover how the Lord ſtretched the line of confuſion and the ſtones of emptineſſe over all ſuch conſtitutions and intereſts as had been props and pillars for the upholding the old Antichriſtian and worldly pomp, pride and greatneſſe; if the aim and tendencie of theſe Providences be conſidered, it is eaſie to gheſſe what the Work of God is at this day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourth Rule.</hi> Take notice what things have fallen out upon a People among us ſince they left the Work of the Lord, they were firſt about, to build their own houſes, ſince they left their firſt love, and labour, and patience, and zeal in that Work, and are joyned to another Intereſt: As ſoon as <hi>Saul</hi> failed in the Work of the Lord, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.14. <hi>The Spirit of the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from Saul, and an evil ſpirit from the Lord troubled him:</hi> That Spirit he had for the Lord, and the work of Reformation, left him, and he was turned to hate the ſame Spirit when it came upon <hi>David:</hi> It is a true obſervation, where the Spirit of God is ſeen in the moſt gracious, lively and warmeſt workings of it, there are the choiceſt Servants of God, and there is his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49600:11"/> Work carrying on. What a bleſſed Spirit was there upon a People among us? What zeal did it work? what indignation? what godly ſorrow for miſcarriages? what purging of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the old leaven? what preſſing on towards a thorow Reformation, and the good things of the latter dayes, how is this Spirit (I would I could not ſay it) departed from them.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But wherein does it appear that that Spirit has left them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It appears by their principles and deſigns; the Spirit of God acts upon holy and gracious Principles, and unto holy and noble ends; a People led by the Spirit of God do act up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch Principles as are ſpiritual, the Word of God, Faith in the Promiſes, Love to Chriſt, to his Saints, to the breathings of the Spirit in them, to Righteouſneſs and Holineſs; now where you ſee theſe Principles left and ſlighted, and others took up, worldly power, and pollicy, and conjunction with them, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther left the Work formerly, or were enemies to it, and practiſes tending to pour contempt upon the bleſſed Cauſe and Intereſt of Chriſt among us, and upon all thoſe that would ſtill be faithful to it, untill the Kingdomes of this World become the Kingdome of our Lord; this is not the Spirit of God you may be aſſured, that does ſuch things: The ſpirits of any thing are known by the breath or ſavour it yeilds; <hi>Thou ſavoureſt not the things that be of God, but the things that be of man:</hi> where we find a ſtrong ſcent and ſavour in our own hearts, or others, of the fleſh-pots, and onyons, an hankering after the treaſures of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the pomp, preferments, titles, and honors, the conſtitutions and intereſts of thoſe that the Lord caſt out before us, to be like the Nations, in Government, State, Deſigns, and Manners, there we may fear the Spirit of the Lord, as to any further work, is departed: More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, ſince many left off following the Lord fully, we ſee not our ſigns and tokens of Gods wonder working Providence as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly; <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.16, <hi>Wherein ſhall it be known here, that I and thy People have found grace in thy ſight, is it not in that thou goeſt with us, ſo ſhall we be ſeparated, I and thy People, from all the People that are upon the face of the earth:</hi> Whilſt there was a People among us that were faithful with the Lord and his Saints, and had a heart to the glorious things God hath for his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49600:12"/> Church, the Lord Jeſus went forth before them as General, and put the feir of them upon all that were about them: but ſince then, what frowns from Heaven? what tokens of diſpleaſure have been upon us both at Sea and Land? whereby all things drive heavily, at home fears and confuſion, abroad waſting and conſuming upon their Armies; now obſerve, in what walk and way we had the Lord preſent among us, and how ſince then he has withdrawn himſelf from us, and thence we may gather where his Work lies at this day.</p>
            <p>Now then if you judge theſe Rules to be ſuch, as may give any certain light to reſolve us in the queſtion; The Work the Lord our God is about at this day is a choice Work, and a great Work, and beyond the ordinary wayes and Diſpenſations of God in times paſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Lord is forming a People for himſelf, purifying and fitting a People to follow Chriſt in thoſe ſpecial Services, wherein his Glory is more eminently concerned; if the Works that God has done in the midſt of us be in order to ſome greater things he has yet to do, then will he ſanctifie and prepare a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that ſhall underſtand the Work of the Lord, and ſerve him therein; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.2. <hi>Rule thou in the midſt of thine Enemies, thy People ſhall be willing in the day of thy power, in the beauties of holineſs:</hi> They that ſhall be of the moſt ready and willing ſpirit to ſerve Chriſt in the Work of his Kingdom, ſhall be a People of more grace and holineſs then others, a People that ſhall have Faith and Love to Chriſt, and Zeal for his Kingdom, and Glory, burning more upon their hearts then others have. The Promiſes ſhew of this thing frequently; <hi>Iſai.</hi> 4.3. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſſe, that he that is left in Sion, and he that remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in Jeruſalem, ſhall be called holy, even every one that is written among the living in Jeruſalem:</hi> When the Lord is about to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh his Church above all Mountains, all other Kingdomes and People in the World, he will firſt cauſe them to ſeparate and come out from the ſins and uncleanneſſes of the World, and will make them a People fitted to enjoy the glory of that day, to be as Saviours upon Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> and to judge the Mount of <hi>Eſau:</hi> The Warrs and changes that have been among us call for this too, they have been as fires to purifie us from our ſins and Idols, though many are ſince gone back to commit fornication with
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49600:12"/> them again: The deſolations and troubles that do at this time threaten the Nations all about us, ſeem to be as ſignes and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens to all that are wiſe hearted among us, to prepare to meet the Lord Jeſus in his Judgements; he is above, when ye ſee theſe things begin to come to paſſe, then lift up your heads and look up.</p>
            <p>This will be better underſtood, by making a more particular enquiry, what manner of Work that is, wherein God will fit his People, and make them ready to follow Jeſus Chriſt in the things he is about:</p>
            <p>Firſt, We may look that he will put another ſpirit upon his People then that is, which is generally found at this day among the People of God; a choſen People, a picked People become thoſe Works God has promiſed to do in the latter dayes: If an Honorable Perſon had a Negotiation which concerned his Honour and Eſtate, he would employ ſuch Perſons about it, as would become ſuch a Maſter, and of abilities for ſuch a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. Or if a great Prince were about to ſhew himſelf openly, to be ſeen before his Subjects, he would chooſe a Train of ſuch Perſons, to attend upon him, as ſhould ſet off the glory and ſplendor of his Royal Perſon before the people: The Works wherein the Lord Jeſus will glorifie himſelf, and be more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently exalted, he will chooſe ſuch choice and precious Saints and Servants to be about him therein, as that by the Grace and Bleſſedneſs which they ſhall ſhew forth, his Glory ſhall ſhine forth the more; there is ſo much droſs and Tin mingled with our Gold, ſo much of worldly ſpirit, in exceſs, pomp, deſigns, ſeeking and receiving honour and promotions; ſo much of a carnal frame, in debates, envyings, ſtripes, backbitings, whiſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, ſwellings, tumults; and ſo much of an Antichriſtian ſpirit is found among us, in joyning intereſts with <hi>Babylon,</hi> confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies with her Kings, building up again her horned power, hanker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after her cuſtomes, manners, laws, worldly ſplendor and greatneſs, that whilſt we are in ſuch a condition as this, God will commit no eminent or ſpecial ſervice or truſt unto us; ſuch a people are not in a condition, fit to attend upon the Lord Jeſus in his great Works he has to do among us: Whilſt the People of God among us were ſeeking after ſome better things in the Spirit of Grace, with Faith, Singleneſs, and Purity, the Lord
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49600:13"/> was among them by a very gracious and wonderful Preſence, but ſith they have left their firſt Loves, and have forgot their firſt Works, and are ſat down in the middle way, the Lord is ſeeking a People of another ſpirit, who will follow him fully in the Works he has promiſed to do in theſe laſt days: Now we may know ſuch a People, a People of another ſpirit, where the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing characters are found.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In dayes of diviſion and diſtemper, of corruption and falling away from their firſt Love, fervency of Spirit, the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, ſavour and Spirit of Chriſt, and Goſpel-conformity, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſecurity and reſt; from whence come uncleanneſſe, laſcivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, ſtrife, wrath, and hereſies; a People that in ſuch dayes are growing in their Light, love, Purity, and Zeal for Chriſt, his Work and Kingdom, are a People of another Spirit, of ſuch a Spirit as the Lord ſeeks for, for ſuch a Spirit was <hi>Paul,</hi> and ſome few in his time.</p>
            <p n="2">2. After a Reformation has begun in the Churches of God, when the old leaven the conſtitutions and cuſtomes made in the time of Antichriſtian blindneſs and Idolatry are eſtabliſht and kept up among them; or when a People in a Nation, who were coming out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> delivered from the yoaks, and by a great deal of conviction, through many wonders of Providence, called to come out of the corruptions of the World, ſhall return back again to bondage, either by confederacies with <hi>Babylons</hi> friends, mingling with their manners, or taking the golden wedge, if in ſuch dayes as this there be any that continue in their love and zeal to Jeſus Chriſt, his Kingdom, a thorow Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of things, until all power be put into his hands, and do ſhew forth the ſame, by following all holy and righteous wayes and means, for the promoting thereof in the World, ſuch are a people of another ſpirit; ſuch a ſpirit as this was in <hi>Elijah, Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas, David, Nehemiah,</hi> and ſome others in their time, and in the worthy Reformers of later times: <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10. <hi>I will pour upon them the ſpirit of grace and ſupplication, and they ſhall look upon me who they have pierced and ſhall mourn for him:</hi> The Lord will have ſuch a people as ſhall be deeply affected with Chriſt, and with a ſenſe of the diſhonor and reproach that lies upon him, his cauſe and intereſt in theſe laſt times.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49600:13"/>3. When the ſigns of the times are not diſcerned nor heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor the Works and Mind of God pointed at thereby is not cloſed withall, a great ſecurity and unbelief, and a lazy luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm indifferency, generally prevailing, as to the things which concern the promiſed Kingdom and Glory of Chriſt, and the overturning of all that which letteth; whoſoever ſhall then be found upon their watch, in ſupplications and ſearchings, mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the ſins of the times, refuſing to bow to the Kings Image, opening their window towards <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that is, praying for the Redemption of the Church of Chriſt, and enquiring out the time, ſuch are a people of another ſpirit, ſuch a people the Lord ſeeks for, as a people fit to follow him, &amp; wait upon him; of ſuch an excellent ſpirit was <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the men of <hi>Iſſachar, Noah, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah,</hi> and others: As he is a man of a mean, low, baſe ſpirit, that can be content Chriſt ſhould have a little place in his heart, and the old Man a great deal, ſo it is a note of a people of a low and unworthy ſpirit, not fit for any eminent ſervice for Chriſt, that are content with a little of Chriſts Righteouſneſs and Reformation in a Nation, well ſatisfied ſo they may live in peace, and eaſe, and plenty, though Chriſt have not the ſway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, over-ruling Power in the publick and higheſt matters that are done among them: When a deep ſleep of ſecurity in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent things has taken hold upon many, then to have the eyes open, and heart awake, preſſing forward towards things before, is a ſign of a people of another ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A people that follow the Lord fully which way ſoever he goes, that whilſt others are taken off by fear of difficulty, worldly advantage, or ſome cunning pretences, will not be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with to decline or caſt off the Lord and the Work he is about, ſuch are a people of another ſpirit; whilſt Rulers, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and Churches were all as one for the Work of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus among us, and many outward ſucceſſes and incouragements were caſt in, and the owning thereof was the way to advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the World, an ordinary and common ſpirit might fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Lord in ſuch a day; but when all theſe props and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations are ſhaken, and the ſtreams of intereſts &amp; affairs is turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into another channel, againſt the Work and Promiſe of God, then to be lovers and followers of the Lord Jeſus, his glorious Cauſe and Intereſt, when it lies under ſuch contempt and death,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49600:14"/> as this is the work of a very choice and excellent ſpirit, when the Spies returned, <hi>Numb.</hi> 13.27. <hi>They told Moſes, and ſaid, we came unto the Land, whither thou ſenteſt us, and ſurely it floweth with Milk and Honey, and this is the fruit of it; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe the people be ſtrong that dwell in the Land, and the Cities are walled, and very great; and moreover we ſaw the children of Anak there; and all Iſrael cryed and wept that night, and ſaid, let us make a Captain, and let us return into Egypt;</hi> but <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Joſhua</hi> were of another ſpirit: By the taſtes we have had of Goſpel light and Reformation, of the Government of Chriſt Kingdom of late, very many are ready to ſay, that the Land is good and pleaſant, for Gods People to be under a Government of Gods making, under Rulers of Gods annointing is bleſſed; as it is but a reaſonable thing; but this Kingdom (ſay they) being not of this World, will not be received nor ſubjected to by the World, nor can it be ſet up but by a ſhaking and pulling to pieces the Kingdomes of the World, as to the foundation they now ſtand upon; wherefore it being a buſineſs of ſo great trouble, difficulty, and danger, before it can be attained, let us make (ſay many among us) a Captain, and let us return into <hi>Egypt,</hi> or let us ſit down on this ſide <hi>Iordan,</hi> with the enjoyment of our eaſe and quiet, rather then ſeek or make out after ſuch a Kingdom with the loſſe of all: This is a low unworthy Spirit, having little love to the Glory and Excellency of Chriſt and his Kingdom; the Lord will prepare a People of another Spirit, that will ſtrengthen one another to go on, until all the Enemies of Chriſt and his People be put under our feet.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As the Lord will chooſe among his People ſuch as are of another Spirit, ſo he will have a People of more refined and excellent Principles then are commonly found among us; Principles are the ſprings of Actions, no man can act above his Principles; a man of gracious, noble, and refined Principles is appointed for ſome excellent ſervice and finer work then other men; now the excellency of a mans Principles lies in their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituality, in how much they have of Chriſt and Grace above other men: A man that has more communion with God, with free-grace in Chriſt then others, is a man of more excellent Principles. Mens Principles cannot alwayes be judged by their Profeſſion, but their Profeſſion may be judged off by their
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49600:14"/> Principles: a man of low and ſervile Principles may make a great ſhew and high profeſſion before the World, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> when brought out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> having received the Oracles, having ſeen great Wonders, no Nation like to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yet had in them a ſtrong ſence and ſavour of <hi>Egypt</hi> ſtill in their hearts, they went back to <hi>Egypt;</hi> ſo we of this Nation have been a People of great deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances, under aſtoniſhing Diſpenſations, ſo that it was ſaid of us, what Nation like to ours? what Mercies like to <hi>Englands</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies? Yet we are generally of low, ſervile, ſlaviſh and fearful Principles, ſavouring much of that ſtate whereunto we were firſt in Bondage; how and who in our Principles are below the Diſpenſations that have been upon us, and the work of God has further to do in the World, may appear by conſidering what Principles they are that do prevail moſt at this day among us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They may be known what they are by our ſitting down in an outward ſtate of peace, quiet, and ſafety, well contented and at eaſe therein, while a full and thorow Reformation, and the Mercies promiſed to the Church in the latter dayes, are not ſought after: <hi>David</hi> was of far other Principles, of a choicer Spirit, 2 <hi>Sam,</hi> 7.1, 2. <hi>And it came to paſſe, when the King ſat in his houſe, and the Lord had given him reſt round about from all his enemies; yet the King ſaid unto Nathan the Prophet, See now, I dwell in an houſe of Cedar, but the Ark of God dwelleth within Curtains:</hi> This Principle is wanting, where an outward delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and peace is ſo uſed and ſat down in, as yet the Work of the Lord is not carried on; <hi>Though thou haſt lain among the pets, I will make thee as the wings of a Dove; I will pour out my Spirit upon all fleſh; henceforth there ſhall no more come into thee the uncircumciſed and the unclean:</hi> Great goodneſs is promiſed to the Church in the latter dayes, the Spirit of grace, delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, enlargement, dominion, and exaltation; theſe things were ſought after by the People of God among us of late, and in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance thereof they went ſome dayes journeys, following the Lord through dark and dangerous paths, but are now ſat down by the way, in a low, wearied, unbelieving, and ſlaviſh Spirit, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving little or no ſpirit to the things formerly preſſed after, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.14, 15. <hi>Iſſachar is a ſtrong Aſſe, couching down between two burthens: and he ſaw that reſt was good, and the Land that it was pleaſant, and bowed his ſhoulder to bear, and he became a ſeavant
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49600:15"/> unto tribute:</hi> But <hi>Dan ſhall judge his people as one of the Tribes of Iſrael:</hi> In like manner after a little breathing ſpace has been given us from our former troubles, finding that reſt was good, and a condition of quiet and peace was ſought, ſo that we might enjoy our ceiled houſes, lands, offices, merchandizing, &amp;c. how are many among us willing to put their necks again under the yoaks, and to deliver up, and let go the opportunity and power that was in their hands to have redeemed themſelves, and to have raiſed up that Work and Building, the foundation whereof was laid with the price of ſo much precious bloud.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, What is that Work that is to be carried on? It is ſaid, the Iron was mixt without Clay; it ſhould ſignifie the heatheniſh worldly Civil Power, and the Eccleſiaſtick State ſhould mingle together, the Church ſhould borrow many cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt conſtitutions, cuſtoms, and helps from the wicked and worldly power; this mixture is yet found among us; the old leaven of Antichriſtian pollutions, manners, and proceedings that was begun to be purged out, is leavening us again, even the whole lump (if grace prevent not:) The Baſis upon which God will ſet up his Kingdome, namely, the Word of God, as the Law and the Spirit of Chriſt in his Saints, as the Counſellor, is not admitted: <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.14. <hi>Should we again break thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, and joyn in affinity with the people of theſe abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions?</hi> Whilſt worldly aims and ends run along with the Work of Chriſt, he had many followers; but now that the God of this World hath given to many the golden Cup, whereby they are overcome in ſecurity and eaſe, to make another ſtep in that Work, beyond what the preſent ſtate of things will bear, ſuch love and zeal is found but with few amongſt us, this is a low un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Principle: If the bleſſed Reformers of former Ages, or more later of our times, who alwayes found every new ſtep in Reformation to be attended with difficulty and oppoſition, had been of this low and unſearchable ſpirit, or could have been content for the enjoyment of their lives and liberties, eaſe and pleaſures, with the loſſe of the Goſpel and Reformation in the greater purity of it, we ſhould inſtead of ſeeing the things we have ſeen in our dayes, have been inheriting the blindneſs and bondage of our forefathers: It is worthy to be remembred, while we were a people as one, ſtanding upon an Intereſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49600:15"/> from all Nations about us, the Lord was graciouſly ſought of us, and that his Preſence was nearer his wonderful Works de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, but ſince we have made peace with the Enemies of the Lord, this peace has pierced deeper into our ſides then ever their ſwords before could do; which puts me in mind of what is ſaid, <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.25. <hi>By peace he ſhall deſtroy many:</hi> When An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt ſaw he could not prevail among us by the ſword, through his policy he proſpers, and by peace, and eaſe, and quiet he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes many; wherefore the Lord will have a people of ſuch light, ſincerity and love, as will not be contented with the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able enjoyment of Wives, Children, houſes, Lands, Honors, or Preferments, until the Lord Jeſus in his Laws, Government, Spirit and Saints be exalted over all the Earth, and his glory above the Heavens.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whilſt there is a ſetting up the Maxims and rules of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly corrupt States and Kingdoms, yea though it were the moſt prudent and righteous Principles of (Civil) Intereſt, when this is done to keep down the Work God is about in our day, this is a ſign we are a People of Principles low and unſuitable to the Promiſes and Diſpenſations that we are under; as when the Kingdom of God comes into the heart, the moſt rational and refined Principles or Nature that were there before, muſt give place to the powerful convictions of Grace, and the light of the Spirit; ſo when the Kingdom of God is come forth viſibly in the World, the faſhion and frame of things in Kingdoms and Nations muſt paſſe away before it; and when God is about to do ſuch a Work as this, for any to inſiſt upon the moſt righteous and prudent Principles, to the hinderance of the Work of God, cannot be juſtified: <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.9, 10, 11. <hi>Behold, the people of the children of Iſrael are more and mightier then we, come on, let us deal wiſely with them, leſt they multiply, and it come to paſſe, that where there fall out any warr, they joyn alſo unto our enemies and fight againſt us, and ſo get them up out of the Land: Therefore they did ſet over them Task maſters to afflict them with their bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens:</hi> Herein they exerciſed their wiſdom of State againſt the Work God had in hand, and paid dearly for it: <hi>Judg.</hi> 8.22. <hi>The men of Iſrael ſaid unto Gideon, rule thou over us, both thou, and thy ſon, and thy ſons ſon alſo, for thou haſt delivered us from the hand of Midian.</hi> What a more juſt and reaſonable thing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49600:16"/> could have been thought upon, and more conducing to common ſettlement and ſafety? But obſerve what anſwer was returned verſe 23. <hi>And Gideon ſaid unto them, I will not rule over you, neither ſhall my ſon rule over you, the Lord ſhall rule over you.</hi> A noble and choice Spirit, he looked upon <hi>Iſrael</hi> as under Gods more immediate Government, and any other ſettlement by humane and worldly wiſdom, however pretending to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good, was not by any means to be admitted: I ſhall add only one Inſtance more, <hi>Numb.</hi> 32.5. <hi>Reuben</hi> and <hi>Gad</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Moſes, Let this Land be given unto thy ſervants for a poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and bring us not over Jordan:</hi> Their deſire was juſt and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, for they had many Cattle, and it was a place for Cattle. But <hi>Moſes</hi> anſwered, <hi>Shall your Brethren go to war, and ſhall ye ſit here,</hi> verſe 6. behold ye are riſen up in your Fathers ſtead, an increaſe of ſinful men: <hi>Moſes</hi> having his eye upon the Work the Lord was about, would not indure that any Civil Intereſt, how publick or juſt ſoever, ſhould be taken into any competiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the Lords Work, It was Reaſon of State that ſet up <hi>Ieroboams</hi> Calves for the preſervation of the Kingdom; that erected the Romiſh Chair for preſerving of unity in the Church and the peace of her Kings; that formerly impoſed uniformity of worſhip and other laws upon the Conſcience, and of late new Lords over the Church of God, all deviſed by the Man of Sin, thereby to put a check and ſtop upon the bleſſed Spirit of Chriſt, and work of Reformation, that both theſe might be kept under, and might not grow up to any conſiderable height, for fear of bringing in a change of things into the World: During the time of the Churches being in the Wilderneſs, Kingdomes, and States, and Churches have been left to be ordered by carnal Force and Policy, and at the beſt by the Rules of Morality and Civil Right; and theſe times of ignorance and corruption God winked at: But now that the Kingdomes of this World are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to become the Kingdomes of our Lord, and his Chriſt, it will be the wiſdom of all that fear the Lord, to take heed of ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting down in, or contending for any wayes or intereſts, how juſt and prudent ſoever, againſt the Work and Word of Chriſt that is about to be fulfilled: When the Office and Right of Chriſt, as Prophet and Head of the Church, was brought to light in our dayes among us, what a blow was there given to that corrupt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49600:16"/> ſtate that was before; ſo likewiſe when the Royal Prerogative of Chriſt, as King of Nations, began to be owned in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and publick Affairs among us, how the Lord ſtood by a deſpiſed remnant of his People therein, and how he left and laid aſide all thoſe that ſtick to their State Maxims, to their old Rules, Cuſtoms and bounds <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>to the hindrance of the Work then in hand is well known, wherefore the Lord will have his people purged from the old leaven of theſe low and carnal Principles, and that will not ſit down in any Intereſt or ſettlement, how juſt or ſafe ſoever, whereby a ſtop is or may be put into the Work of God, in the exalting of his Son, in his Word, Works, and bleſſed Spirit among us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That we are a People of Principles below the Works of God in our day, and unſuitable thereunto, may appear by the old pollutions entertained again; from which many ſeemed to have been purged; there is a corrupt mixture with this World, that has ſpread it ſelf through the hearts and lives of moſt, and through the Eccleſiaſtical and Civil State, whereby that holy frame of heart, and work of Reformation, formerly among us, is much laid aſide: A Church or People is ſaid to be holy, when the Word of the Lord is their Law, and when they yield up themſelves unto the Lord all one in all things, to be governed by his Commandements: And on the contrary, it is a People corrupted and unclean, when other Lords beſides Chriſt have dominion over them, and the will and commandement of men is ſet up. The Church of the Old and New Teſtament in their beginning had more of this beauty of holineſs and profeſſed ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection unto the Lord only, then was ever ſeen ſince: <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid of <hi>Iſrael</hi> concerning their firſt eſtate, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.12. <hi>The Lord alone did lead him, and there was no ſtrange God with him:</hi> though <hi>he ſoon forſook God which made him, and lightly eſteemed the Rock of his ſalvation:</hi> So <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of the Church as it was in its firſt eſtate, before the Man of Sin had deflowered it; <hi>I have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſed you to one Husband, that I may preſent you as a chaſt Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to Chriſt:</hi> A looking back unto theſe things, together with a meaſure of the Spirit, vouchſafed in our dayes, did work in the hearts of many among us ſtrong convictions of much blackneſs and deformity, of many pollutions contracted from Antichriſt, yet remaining upon us, and gave light and diſcerning of a more
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49600:17"/> holy reformed and happy eſtate, both commanded and promiſed; and upon this account was there a ſeparation made among us as to Worſhip; firſt from Prelacy, then from the National way, and afterwards as to Government from Monarchy, Gods Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple being led all along herein, and preſſed on from a Principle of Grace and Holineſs, and from ſome light in the Promiſes, which ſpeak of a day when every po<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and in <hi>Judah</hi> ſhall be holineſs unto the Lord, and the Idols he ſhall utterly aboliſh: Whilſt our hearts were under this holy and gracious frame, we were going on to purge out all ſuch mixtures yet remaining a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, as were borrowed from corrupt and Antichriſtian States and Kingdomes, that we might become a new lump, a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly People, a righteous State, juſt Laws and all things reduced as near as might be unto the pattern; but inſtead of going on with theſe firſt Works, we are mingled again with the Idols and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſes of former times, the ſad effects whereof do appear almoſt every where upon the <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and lives of moſt, and upon the Profeſſion and Government that is held out in the Nation: This was the evil of the Church of old, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 106.25. They were mingled among the Heathen, and learned their works: <hi>Hoſea</hi> 7.8. <hi>Ephraim he hath mixed himſelf among the people, Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael is a Cake not turned:</hi> 2 Cor. 6.4. <hi>Be ye not unequally yoak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together with unbelievers, for what fellowſhip hath righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with unrighteouſneſſe; wherefore come out from among them, and be ye ſeparate.</hi> When Gods People began to joyn with the World in Civils, they afterwards joyned with them in Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, until the whole lump was learned. The Reformers of the Church in former and latter times, their Zeal was ſtirred up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe minglings, both in doctrine and manners, againſt the inventions and commandments of men in the one, againſt worldly pomp pleaſures, and ſenſuality in the other: Religion cannot be accommodated to intereſts and reſpects of pollicy and ſerving <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, it cannot be mixt with error, no more then oyl with water, <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and ſt<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> with clay, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.43. It is ſaid, 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>7.3<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. the mingled people of <hi>Samaria feared the Lord and ſerved their God after the manner of the Nations:</hi> But what faith God, doth he approve of this <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ture? verſe 34. God will no town his own commanded Worſhip, when mingled and compounded with another. <hi>[Dr. Preſton.]</hi> Wherefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49600:17"/> the Lord will go on with any further <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t Mercies for his People, he will have a People that ſhall purge out this old <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from among them, that they may be a new lump, as it is ſaid, <hi>Numb.</hi> 23.9. <hi>Lo, the people ſhall dwell alone, and ſhall not be reckoned among the Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another part of that Work the Lord is about among us, is to call his People out from partakings in thoſe ſins that are more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially the ſins of the time and of this Generation. God may have a People ſubject to many infirmities and ſailings, and yea ſuch as have overcome the ſins of the times: Although <hi>Aſa</hi> had offended in divers things, yet as to the times, the heart of <hi>Aſa</hi> was perfect all his dayes, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.17. So there are many ſins that may be ſpoken againſt without offence to the times, but the ſpecial ſins of the Generation are overcome and reproved but by a remnant of another ſpirit. Now if we would rightly judge what are the ſins of the times we live in, this may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded as a ſure Rule; obſerve what have been the more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and ſpecial Diſpenſations and Works of God among us in our day, and ſuch courſes and proceedings among us, whether publick or private, as lie more directly croſſe and contrary there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, are the ſpecial ſins and evils of the time: This being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted for a good Rule in this place, what are the ſpecial ſins of the time, from which the Lord will have his People to come out of, and be ſeparate from, will ſomewhat appear by the Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons following.</p>
            <p>Firſt. After the Lord has begun to waſh away the filth of the Daughter of <hi>Sion,</hi> to purge the Church of Chriſt among us from the fifth of Antichriſtianiſme, and by overturning ſome great Pillars of the Antichriſtian Church and State, has begun a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of things, according to the pattern of the Goſpel and Scripture light, and alſo gave forth a portion of the Spirit for this Work, after ſuch a day as this, to joyn our ſelves again with the people of thoſe abomination, (as it is ſeen at this day) by marriages, leagues, conjunction of their and our Intereſts, by reviving and ſetting up again that old faſhion of things in its conſtitutions, cuſtomes, worldly policies, pomp, greatneſs and luſts, this is one of the ſpecial <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the times, and from which the Lord will have his People to redeem and ſeparate themſelves from, <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.2. <hi>The holy <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> have mingled themſelves with
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49600:18"/> the people of thoſe Lands, yea the hand of the Princes and Rulers hath been chief in this treſpaſſe; and when I heard this thing I rent my garment:</hi> And this was the great ſin of that time, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Work of God in that day.</p>
            <p n="2">2. After that a publick and ſolemn Teſtimony has been born among us, through much bloud and difficulties, and the ſame as eminently owned of God by a ſeries of deliverances againſt the great oppreſſive intereſts that were upon us, to wit, the Law in the preſent conſtitution and adminiſtration of it, Monarchy as a thing unneceſſary, burthenſome, and dangerous, a Court as the ſpring head of oppreſſion, pride and filthineſs, with many other things that might be named, to lay theſe heavy yoaks again upon the necks of our Brethren, under which we our ſelves groaned not long ago, and thereby to ſell the Lords People, with their dear bought power and freedom, the people of the Land, with their juſt rights and liberties, and the Cauſe it ſelf ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for, into the hands of the new Lords, ſtanding upon the old foundation, and acting in moſt points after the old corrupt faſhion of things as formerly; this is a great ſin of the times, for which the Lord cals upon his People to mourn and be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and by withdrawing themſelves as much as may be from ſuch things, to bear a ſeaſonable and faithful Teſtimony againſt them: The Nobles and Rulers of <hi>Judah,</hi> after they were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered out of bondage in <hi>Babylon,</hi> oppreſſed their Brethren, and laid heavy yoaks upon them; this was a ſpecial ſin of that time, and the Lord ſtirred up the ſpirit of <hi>Nehemiah</hi> againſt them: <hi>Neh.</hi> 5.8. <hi>And I ſaid unto them, we, after our abilitie, have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed our Brethren the Iews, which were ſold unto the Heathens, and will you even ſell your brethren, or ſhall they be ſold unto us? Alſo I ſaid, it is not good that ye do, ought ye not to walk in the fear of our God, becauſe of the reproach of the Heathen our enemies?</hi> When God is breaking the yoaks of his People, to be then lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yoaks upon them, is a ſpecial ſin of the time.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Many among us have ſinned in taking the accurſed thing: the meaning whereof, both in the Old and New Teſtament, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports a thing that is ordained of God to deſtruction, a People, or things of Gods Curſe, ſhut out of God protection, and the prayers of his People. Now obſerve what things they were among us that Gods People did formerly caſt out of their
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49600:18"/> heares and prayers, that God did caſt out from under his viſible Diſpenſations of Mercy, that lay under his frowns and terrible dints of his diſpleaſure; as things oppoſite to his Glory, the work of Reformation, and the proſperity and peace of his People, the mingling again with theſe things is a taking the accurſed thing, and one of the ſins of the times: <hi>Ier.</hi> 7 16. <hi>Pray not thou for this people, neither lift up a cry nor prayer for them:</hi> We may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what the Lords choice and faithful Servants among us did formerly leave out, as things they could not pray for, what conſtitutions and intereſts in the State? what pomp, covetouſneſs and exceſs among men in eminent place? What mixtures and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malitie in worſhip? and what Idols and humane Statues in Gods Houſe? and are not theſe things, and that old Spirit that acted them, revived again, whereby the Lord has been provoked to bring a cloud upon us, and upon that day of Mercies and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful appearances, whereby his Work was carried on among us. So then obſerve, what things they are that the Lords more peculiar and praying People formerly, or at this day, under their more enlightened, holy and zealous frame could not, or do not pray for, but leave out, and ſeparate themſelves from, and they are that curſed thing which we ought to come out of and avoid.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The putting back of that bleſſed Work, that was in ſuch a hopeful way to be carried on among us, is a great ſin of the times; when I conſider what an edge was upon the Spirits of good men, how quick and powerful were proceedings, what a ſpirit for high and great Work, a reforming ſpirit for Reforming work, a ſpirit of Judgment for the work of Juſtice, a ſpirit of Prayer for the breaking of all yoaks and deliverance of <hi>Sion,</hi> the whole Church of God, and what a ſeal Providence it ſelf put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all this in a ſeries of wonderful ſucceſſes; and further, that theſe things were come to that height, that the People of God begun to meditate and expect great things, men of low and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſpirits were laid aſide, the old ſpotted and wrinkled face of things, unholineſs and formality in Religion; in the State, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy its Friends and Paramouts, with all its limbs and bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and paintings begun to bluſh and hide it ſelf; I ſay, when I look back at theſe things, and conſider how all this Work is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted and laid aſide, covered under reproach, and buried out of ſight and mind, and only a few left to keep it upon the heart. I
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49600:19"/> cannot but ſadly reflect upon that word, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 9.1. <hi>Rejoyce not O Iſrael for joy, as other people, for thou haſt gone a whoring from thy God, thou haſt loved a reward upon every corn floor.</hi> There is a nick of time, a ſpecial ſeaſon, wherein God cals, and employes, and ſpirits people for his Work; if this time be not obſerved, both the Work and opportunity for it is loſt, and things will go backward; When <hi>Saul</hi> ſlipped in the Work God had called him unto, he loſt the Spirit of the Lord, and the work of his day alſo: So when <hi>Iſraels</hi> faith failed in the matter of the Spies, and in their hearts gave back from following the Lord, the Work was put back for forty years: in like manner let it be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, what a door was opened, by the mighty Works of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, to have let in a ſeaſon of Mercies, to have proceeded to a full and thorow Reformation, to have removed all lets and obſtructions, and to have ſet the higheſt and moſt publick Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts and greateſt Affairs upon another, a better baſt and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation then they had ſtood upon before, whereon the Intereſt of Chriſt, his Saints, his Word, as the Law and Rule, might have been eminently owned and exerciſed among us; the Promiſes, that the Saints ſhall take the Kingdom, and the Kingdom ſhall not be left to another People, calling upon all Gods People to have reſpect unto this, as the great Intereſt, to be above all other contended after; but they who had this price formerly in their hand, and an heare unto it, have let their opportunity ſlip, and that Spirit they had for this Work is departed, the work is gone many degrees back, and becauſe of their and our ſins, the good things that were in the birth are kept from us: When <hi>Iſrael</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired a King, one might have pleaded for them, and ſaid, they think no evil, they do but deſire another form of Government, as more expedient for them then that of Judges: Nay but ſayes the Lord, <hi>They have rejected me that I ſhould nor reign over them,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam</hi> 8.7 They rejected the Diſpenſation it ſelf they were under, as too holy and divine; this was their ſin, they ſaid, <hi>Now make us a King to judge us like all the Nations;</hi> they would not be a ſeparate people they would look like the Nations: Wiſe men do not look upon the change of perſons, and names, and form of Government that has been among us, ſo much, as that the Diſpenſation we were under, in the very nature of it, as it was more holy, and ſpiritual, and refined, is rejected; not the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49600:19"/> only of the Work among us is altered, but the matter of it is gone, and another thing ſet up in its place, this is a ſin of the times we ought to mourn over and avoid.</p>
            <p n="5">5. To name no more; the heart of the people of that part of the People that were forward and active in the Work is wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered and ſunk into a low and unſenſible frame; an impotent, low and unworthy ſpirit is fallen upon many, willing to fit at eaſe, though in a low and ſlaviſh ſtate, that can look upon the deſpiſed, deſerted Cauſe and Intereſt of Chriſt without any trouble of heart, or a cry, or a prayer for it; there are but a few who have in them at this day thoſe workings and yearnings of heart, in looking upon a crucified Cauſe, as <hi>Mary</hi> and the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples had over their crucified Friend the Lord Jeſus: When any eminent work was to be done in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the Lord firſt ſet it upon the hearts of ſome, and ſtirred up the ſpirit of the people unto it: Ye that make mention of the Lord, keep not ſilence, and give him no reſt till he make <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a praiſe in the earth: The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance of the Church in the <hi>Revelations, chap.</hi> 14.2. begins with a voice from the waters, the ſpirits of the people are ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up to ſtand up with the Lamb on Mount <hi>Sion:</hi> When there was a raiſing and ſtirring in the ſpirits of many in our dayes, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the work of Juſtice and Reformation, how great things were brought forth in that day? But now that preſſing and ſtirring work in the hearts of moſt, and the good things it tended to is caſt off and gone, the leſſe thereof is ſo farre from working any due reſentment among us, as that where any remainders of that good old Spirit are yet breathing in any, they are laid aſide, and caſt into corners, as the fire-brands and troublers of the times, though it is only againſt the corruptions of the times; that they do appear, and that from their love to Chriſt and holineſs. Theſe are ſome of the ſins of the times, from which we are to come out of and be ſeparate.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
